A Guide to the Russell Sage Foundation records, Microfiche Collection FA1841
Rockefeller Archive Center
Russell Sage Foundation records, Microfiche Collection
1894-1955
1907-1947
Rockefeller Archive Center
Russell Sage Foundation
FA1841
0.14 Cubic Feet 379 microfiche cards
379 microfiche cards.
Scope and Contents
This microfiche collection, filmed by UPA Academic Editions, primarily documents the activities of the Russell Sage Foundation from its inception in 1907 through their admininstrative restructuring in 1947.
This collection is comprised of publications, including pamphlets and series, select historical documents from the RSF archives at Rockefeller Archive Center, and a complete set of minutes of the Board of Trustees and Executive Committee meetings from 1907-1947.
Monographs, books, and other library items were not filmed as part of this microfiche collection, but microfilm of select library items are available elsewhere in the Russell Sage Foundation collection at Rockefeller Archive Center.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with brittle or damaged items available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged as received, in series or subseries by subject/topic.
- History and Genesis of the Russell Sage Foundation, 1907-1946 (Box 1, Card 1-H (1-2))
  Scope and Contents
  Includes publications or documents written by: John M. Glenn; Lillian Brandt; F. Emerson Andrews; and Frank Tucker.
- Departmental Pamphlet Series, 1905-1946
  - Charity Organization Department, 1905-1943 (Box 1, Card 101-CO (1-81))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Frederick Almy; Porter R. Lee; Alexander Johnson; Francis H. McLean; Margaret F. Byington; Edward T. Devine; Jacob A. Riis; George Hodges; C. C. Carstens; Mary E. Richmond; Ada Eliot Sheffield; Fred S. Hall; James H. Tufts; Samuel M. Crothers; Alexander M. Wilson; Mabel Tibbott; George S. Wilson; Shelby M. Harrison; Joanna C. Colcord.
  - Department of Child Helping, 1909-1924 (Box 1, Card 102-CH (1-52))
    Includes publications or documents written by: William H. Pear; Henry Dwight Chapin; J. W. Schereschewsky; Hastings H. Hart; Milton A. Gerschel; Ellen C. Babbitt; Henry H. Goddard; Frances Sage Bradley; William H. Slingerland; Florence L. Lattimore; C. C. Carstens; William J. Doherty; Ruth W. Lawton; J. Prentice Murphy; Henry H. Hibbs, Jr.; C. Spenser Richardson; Clarence I. Stonaker; G. Croft Williams; Ogden Chisolm; J. F. Wright; Hornell Hart; Charles L. Chute; V. Everett Macy; B. C. Riley; William Hodson; Emma O. Lindberg; Frances Ingram; George A. Hall.
  - Department of Delinquency and Penology, 1926; 1928; 1930 (Box 1, Card 103-DP (1-3))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Hastings H. Hart; Robert Mitts.
  - Department of Child Hygiene, 1907-1914 (Box 1, Card 104-Chy (1-134))
    Includes publications or documents written by: George E. Johnson; Charles Mulford Robinson; Amalie Hofer; Beulah Kennard; Howard Bradstreet; Arthur Leland; E. B. DeGroot; George A. Hibbard; Allen Burns; Harriet Hickox Heller; Woods Hutchinson; Luther H. Gulick; William H. Maxwell; Joseph Lee; Everett W. Lord; Charles E. Hughes; Joseph Lee; Lee F. Hanmer; Ben B. Lindsey; Myron T. Scudder; Hiram H. Edgerton; Austin E. Griffiths; Leonard P. Ayres; George W. Wingate; Elmer Elsworth Brown; Lorna H. Leland; Earl Cline; Mrs. Isaac L. Rice; James Roscoe Day; August H. Brunner; D. A. Sargent; William Orr; Ira J. Gardner; Michael M. Davis, Jr.; Glen Edwards; Clarence A. Perry; William Chauncey Langdon.
  - Department of Recreation, 1913-1935 (Box 1, Card 105-Rec (135-160))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Clarence A. Perry; Lee F. Hanmer; Howard R. Knight; Marguerita P. Williams; Robert K. Atkinson; H. J. Grumpelt.
  - Department of Education, 1913-1921 (Box 1, Card 106-E (135-144))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Leonard P. Ayres; W. Randolph Burgess; Mary Ayres Burgess.
  - Department of Industrial Studies - Women's Work, 1914-1922; 1942; 1947 (Box 1, Card 107-IS (1-9))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Amy Hewes; Mary van Kleeck; Henriette R. Walter; Ben M. Selekman; Louis Bloch; Edward A. Wieck.
  - Department of Library Pamphlets, 1930; 1931; 1938; 1941 (Box 1, Card 108-L (1-4))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Bertha Hulseman.
  - Department of Remedial Loans, 1908-1935 (Box 1, Card 109-RL (1-46))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Clarence W. Wassam; Arhur H. Ham; Malcolm W. Davis; L. G. Robinson; Alphonse Desjardins; R. S. Hale; Earl E. Eubank; Morris Ceasar; Walter S. Hilborn; Leonard G. Robinson; Rolf Nugent; Frank R. Hubachek.
  - Department of Consumer Credit, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Card 110-CC (1-2))
    Includes publications or documents written by: John E. Hamm.
  - Department of Social Interpretation, 1937 (Box 1, Card 111-SWI-1)
    Includes publications or documents written by: Helen C. Baker; Mary Swain Routzahn.
  - Southern Highlands Division, 1917; 1921; 1929 (Box 1, Card 112-SH (1-3))
    Includes publications or documents written by: John C. Campbell.
  - Department of Statistics, 1926-1946 (Box 1, Card 113-St (1-20))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Ralph G. Hurlin.
  - Department of Studies in the Professions, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Card 114-SP (1-2))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Esther Lucile Brown; Eric F. Schweinberg.
  - Department of Surveys and Exhibits, 1912-1931 (Box 1, Card 115-SE (1-32))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Paul U. Kellog; Shelby M. Harrison; George T. Palmer; Zenas L. Porter; Franz Schneider, Jr.; D. O. Decker; Leonard P. Ayres; Walter L. Treadway; Lee F. Hanmer; C. A. Perry; John Ihlder; Francis H. McLean; Louis Odencrantz; Donald B. Armstrong; Louis I. Dublin; Mary Swain Routzahn; Evart G. Routzahn.
  - Department of Social Work Yearbook, 1937; 1946-1947 (Box 1, Card 116-YB (1-3))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Philip E. Ryan; James Dahir.
  - Non-Departmental Pamphlets, 1936-1946 (Box 1, Card 117-ND (1-4))
    Includes publications or documents written by: Shelby M. Harrison; Jeffrey R. Brackett.
- Prevention of Blindness Committee, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Card 118-PBC (1-2))
- Field Department Bulletin, 1911 (Box 1, Card 119-FDB-1)
- Charity Organization Bulletin, 1909-1918 (Box 1, Card 120-COB (1-9))
- Social Case Histories, 1920 (Box 1, Card 121-SCH-1)
- Selected Materials from the Russell Sage Foundation Archives, 1894-1955
  - Mrs. Sage's Early Charitable Activities, 1894-1920 (Box 1, Card 200-H-1 (1-10))
    Documents gifts from, and biographical information about, Margaret Olivia Sage.
  - Genesis of Russell Sage Foundation, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Card 200-H-2 (1-29))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Margaret Olivia Sage; Robert W. deForest; Jeffrey R. Brackett; Henry W. deForest; C. A. Herter; John M. Glenn; Frank Tucker; Franklin Pierce; Lawrence Veiller; George A. Davis; Robert C. Pruyn; Charles E. Hughes; Gertrude S. Rice; Louisa Lee Schuyler.
  - Biographies of Trustees and Staff, 1907-1947 (Box 1, Card 200-H-3 (1-2))
    Includes biographical sketches of: Leonard P. Ayres; Lindsey Bradford; Lilian Brandt; Margaret F. Byington; John C. Campbell; Olive D. Campbell; Joseph P. Chamberlain; Harry W. Chase; Joanna C. Colcord; Eli Whitney Debevoise; Johnston deForest; Robert W. deForest; Frederic A. Delano; Cleveland H. Dodge; Allen H. Eaton; John M. Glenn; John H. Finley; Daniel C. Gilman; Luther H. Gulick; Morris Hadley; Fred S. Hall; Arthur H. Ham; Lee F. Hanmer; Shelby M. Harrison; Hastings H. Hart; Leon Henderson; Donald S. Howard; Frederick Jenkis; Russell H. Kurtz; Francis H. McLean; Robert M. MacIver; Dave H. Morris; Dwight W. Morrow; Charles Dyer Norton; Rolf Nugent; Robert C. Ogden; Clarence A. Perry; Lawson Purdy; Mary Ellen Richmond; Evart G. Routzahn; Mary S. Routzahn; Louisa Lee Schuyler; Helen Gould Shepard; Mary van Kleeck; Alfred T. White; Harold T. White.
  - Histories of the Russell Sage Foundation, 1915-1967 (Box 1, Card 200-H-4 (1-5))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Lilian Brandt. Franz Schneider, Jr.; John M. Glenn; Shelby M. Harrison; Orville Brim.
  - Charity Organization Department, 1907-1947 (Box 1, Card 201-CO (1-32))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Francis H. McLean; Mary E. Richmond; Robert W. deForest; John M. Glenn; Edward T. Devine; Fred S. Hall; Ada E. Sheffield; Joseph Lee; Jeffrey R. Brackett; Rev. Worth M. Tibby; Russell H. Kurtz; Shelby H. Harrison; Donald S. Howard; Ralph G. Hurlin.
  - Child Helping Department, 1907-1923 (Box 1, Card 202-CH (1-21))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Hastings H. Hart; John M. Glenn; Julia C. Lathrop; William H. Slingerland; Thomas E. Kilby; William Hodson.
  - Department of Delinquency and Penology, 1921-1933 (Box 1, Card 203-DP (1-6))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Hastings H. Hart. Hastings H. Hart to John M. Glenn. Hastings H. Hart to Shelby M. Harrison.
  - Child Hygiene Department, 1907-1912 (Box 1, Card 204-Chy (1-16))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Luther H. Gulick. Luther H. Gulick to John M. Glenn. Lee F. Hanmer to John M. Glenn.
  - Department of Recreation, 1911-1938 (Box 1, Card 205-Rec (1-11))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Clarence A. Perry. Lee F. Hanmer to John M. Glenn. Clarence A. Petty to Shelby M. Harrison.
  - Department of Education, 1909-1919 (Box 1, Card 206-E (1-8))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Leonard P. Ayres. Leonard P. Ayres to John M. Glenn.
  - Department of Industrial Studies, 1911-1947 (Box 1, Card 207-IS (1-51))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Mary van Kleeck; John M. Glenn; Florence L. Lattimore; Shelby M. Harrison; Joannna Colcord; Lawson Purdy; Mary L. Fledderus.
  - Library, 1912-1947 (Box 1, Card 208-L (1-5))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Homer Folks; John M. Glenn; Shelby M. Harrison; Charles S. Johnson; Rusell Kurtz.
  - Department of Remedial Loans, 1911-1937 (Box 1, Card 209-RL (1-35))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Arthur H. Ham; John M. Glenn; Andrew Carnegie; Henry S. Pritchett; Walter S. Hilborn; Louis N. Robinson; C. H.Watts; Leon Henderson; L. C. Harbison; Rolf Nugent; Shelby M. Harrison; Thomas E. Dewey.
  - Department of Consumer Credit Studies, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Card 210-CC (1-20))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Rolf Nugent; Shelby M. Harrison; J. Glenn Donaldson; Lindsay Bradford; Joseph P. Chamberlain; J. P. Lewis; James L. Sullivan; George C. Wallace.
  - Department of Social Work Integration, 1935-1947 (Box 1, Card 211-SWI (1-7))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Mary S. Routzahn; Shelby M. Harrison; Leo A. Davis.
  - Southern Highlands Division, 1908-1924 (Box 1, Card 212-SH (1-31))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John C. Campbell; John M. Glenn; Cecil J. Sharp; Katharine Pettit; Rev. James H. Taylor; Olive D. Campbell; George E. Scott.
  - Division of Statistics, 1914-1937 (Box 1, Card 213-ST (1-7))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Earle Clark; John M. Glenn; Ralph G. Hurlin.
  - Department of Studies in the Professions, 1937-1946 (Box 1, Card 214-SP (1-12))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Shelby M. Harrison; Ralph G. Hurlin; Charles E. Merriam; Esther L. Brown; Edward Levi; F. D. G. Ribble; Robert E. Mathews; Esther L. Brown.
  - Department of Surveys and Exhibits, 1912-1919 (Box 1, Card 215-SE (1-8))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Shelby M. Harrison; John M. Glenn; Paul Kellogg.
  - Social Work Year Book, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Card 216-YB (1-3))
  - Department of Arts and Social Work, 1929-1946 (Box 1, Card 217-ASW (1-18))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Shelby M. Harrison; Allen Eaton.
  - Regional Plan and Survey of New York City and its Environs, 1921-1944 (Box 1, Card 218-RP (1-40))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Shelby M. Harrison; John M. Glenn; Charles D. Norton; Evart G. Routzahn; Mary S. Routzahn; Lewis Mumford; Robert W. deForest; Frederic A. Delano; Thomas Adams; Robert Moses; Clifford L. Jackson; Thomas A. McWhinney; Frederic A. Delano; F. Emerson Andrews; Lawrence M. Orton; George McAneny.
  - Housing - Forest Hills Gardens, 1908-1939 (Box 1, Card 219-Hs-1 (1-21))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Robert W. deForest; Frederick Law Olmstead; Grosvenor Atterbury; Alfred T. White; William E. Harmon; Edward H. Bouton; John M. Demarest; John M. Glenn; Mary E. Knevels; John M. Demarest; Clarence A. Perry.
  - Housing - Sunnyside Gardens, 1925-1936 (Box 1, Card 219-Hs-2 (1-19))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Johnston deForest; John M. Glenn; W. D. Heydecker; D. E. McAvoy; Shelby M. Harrison; Thomas Adams; Frederick P. Keppel; C. J. Martin; Andrew M. Bing; Lawson Purdy; J. E. Brockway; Robert D. Elder; Rolf Nugent.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Social Work Education, 1909-1928 (Box 1, Card 220-M-1 (1-10))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Porter R. Lee; C. M. Davis; W. H. McClain; Thomas J. Riley; Sophonisba P. Breckinridge; Edith Abbott; Samuel McClure Lindsay; Roswell C. McCrea.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Social Halls, 1909-1913; 1921 (Box 1, Card 220-M-2 (1-4))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Robert W. deForest; Thatcher M. Brown; Gretchen M. Brown; Lillian Wald.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Small Loan Societies, 1909-1939 (Box 1, Card 220-M-3 (1-7))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Robert W. deForest; Cleveland H. Dodge; Arthur H. Ham; Shelby M. Harrison; Jeremiah Milbank; John H. Finley.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - National Employment Exchange, 1909; 1931-1932 (Box 1, Card 220-M-4 (1-4))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Edward T. Devine; Robert W. deForest; Henry L. deForest; L. F. Loree; Shelby M. Harrison.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Relations with Other Organizations, 1912-1914; 1941-1944 (Box 1, Card 220-M-5 (1-4))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Edward T. Devine.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Lewis W. Hine, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Card 220-M-6 (1-6))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Lewis W. Hine; Shelby M. Harrison; Mary S. Routzahn; Paul Kellog; Bertha F. Hulseman.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Willem van de Wall, 1921-1943 (Box 1, Card 220-M-7 (1-6))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Willem van de Wall; John M. Glenn; Lee F. Hanmer; Shelby M. Harrison.
  - Miscellaneous Concerns - Other Concerns, 1907-1944 (Box 1, Card 220-M-8 (1-11))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Louisa Lee Schuyler; Robert W. deForest; Cleveland H. Dodge; Francis H. McLean; Mayo Fesler; William Hodson; Jeffrey R. Brackett; Mary van Kleeck; Edwin R. A. Seligman; William C. Coffin; Johnston deForest; Shelby M. Harrison.
  - Operations and Finances - Grants, 1907-1913; 1935-1947 (Box 1, Card 221-OF-1 (1-8))
    Summary of grants, grant requests, as well as declined grants. Includes publications or documents written by/to: Shelby M. Harrison; Johnston deForest.
  - Operations and Finances - Other Finances, 1907-1955 (Box 1, Card 221-OF-2 (1-5))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Ralph G. Hurlin; F. Emerson Andrews; John M. Glenn; Shelby M. Harrison; Johnston deForest.
  - Operations and Finances - Russell Sage Building, 1943 (Box 1, Card 221-OF-3 (1-2))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: Mary van Kleeck; J. E. Brockway.
  - Operations and Finances - Russell Sage Foundation Employees, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Card 221-OF-4 (1-8))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Lindsay Bradford; Harriet S. Butcher; Charles C. Huitt; Shelby M. Harrison; Carl Hadley; William Piehl; Ralph G. Hurlin; Mary van Kleeck; Clarence King; Bernard Segal.
  - Operations and Finances - Other Policy Matters, 1907-1944 (Box 1, Card 221-OF-5 (1-6))
    Includes publications or documents written by/to: John M. Glenn; Robert W. deForest; Johnston deForest; Shelby M. Harrison.
- Minutes, 1907-1949
  - Board of Trustees, 1907-1949 (Box 1, Card 301-BT)
    The Board of Trustees managed the Russell Sage Foundation's business and assests. The material represented includes: descriptions of grants, records of actions, activities, and appointments, salaries, major policy decisions, and financial statements.
  - Executive Committee, 1907-1949 (Box 1, Card 302-EC)
    The Executive Committee of the Russell Sage Foundation during this period was comprised of the President, the Vice President, and three trustees. It held the power of the Board of Trustees between meetings of the full board, yet met irregularly.
    The material here documents Executive Committee actions which often included preparation of proposals or reports for consideration by the Board of Trustees, as well as any any grant approvals or other considerations directly acted upon by the EC.